but I am one of those .01 percenters
ولكني واحد من نسبة ال 01.
that you hear about and read about,
الذين تسمعون وتقرؤون عنهم
and I am by any reasonable definition a plutocrat.
فأنا أعد بلوتوقراطيا
And tonight, what I would like to do is speak directly
وأريد أن أتحدث مباشرة، هذا المساء
to other plutocrats, to my people,
إلى البلوتوقراطيين الاخرين، إلى أهلي
because it feels like it's time for us all
فيبدو أن الوقت قد حان لنا جميعًا
to have a chat.
لنتحدث
Like most plutocrats, I too am a proud
أنا ايضا متكبر، مثل معظم البلوتوقراطيين
and unapologetic capitalist.
ورأسمالي حتى النخاع
I have founded, cofounded or funded
لقد أسست، وشاركت في تأسيس أو مولت
over 30 companies across a range of industries.
أكثر من 30 شركة في مختلف الصناعات
I was the first non-family investor in Amazon.com.
فقد كنت أول مستثمر خارج العائلة في Amazon.com.
I cofounded a company called aQuantive
وشاركت في تأسيس شركة تدعي aQuantive
that we sold to Microsoft for 6.4 billion dollars.
والتي بعناها لمايكروسوفت ب6.4 مليار دولار
My friends and I, we own a bank.
أمتلك أنا وأصدقائي بنكا
I tell you this — (Laughter) —
أخبركم بهذا - (ضحك) -
unbelievable, right?
لا يصدق، صحيح؟
I tell you this to show
أخبركم بهذا لأبين لكم
that my life is like most plutocrats.
أن حياتي تشبه حياة معظم البلوتوقراطيين
I have a broad perspective on capitalism
لدي منظور واسع تجاه الرأسمالية
and business,
والأعمال
and I have been rewarded obscenely for that
ولهذا فقد منحت العديد من الجوائز
with a life that most of you all
وحياة يعجز أغلبكم
can't even imagine:
عن تخيلها
multiple homes, a yacht, my own plane,
فأمتلك عدة بيوت، ويخت وطائرة خاصة
etc., etc., etc.
الخ، الخ، الخ
But let's be honest: I am not the smartest person you've ever met.
ولكن لنكن صريحين: أنا لست أذكى شخص قابلته في حياتك
I am certainly not the hardest working.
ولا حتى أكثرهم اجتهادا
I was a mediocre student.
لقد كنت تلميذا متوسطا
I'm not technical at all.
ولا أعرف شيئا عن التكنولوجيا على الإطلاق
I can't write a word of code.
لا أستطيع كتابة السطور البرمجية
Truly, my success is the consequence
في الواقع إن نجاحي نتيجة ل:
of spectacular luck,
الحظ الشديد
of birth, of circumstance and of timing.
والنسب والظروف والتوقيت
But I am actually pretty good at a couple of things.
ولكني بارع في بضعة أشياء
One, I have an unusually high tolerance for risk,
أولهم، أنه لدي درجة احتمال عالية للمخاطرة
and the other is I have a good sense,
والثاني أن لدي غريزة جيدة
a good intuition about what will happen in the future,
حدس جيد عما سيحدث مستقبلا
and I think that that intuition about the future
وأظن أن حدس المستقبل هذا
is the essence of good entrepreneurship.
هو جوهر ريادة الأعمال البارعة
So what do I see in our future today,
إذن ماذا يحمل لنا المستقبل في طياته اليوم؟
you ask?
هل تتسألون؟
I see pitchforks,
أنا أرى عصيا،
as in angry mobs with pitchforks,
عصيا تحملها حشود غاضبة
because while people like us plutocrats
فبينما نعيش -نحن البلوتوقراطيون-
are living beyond the dreams of avarice,
حياة تفوق أحلام أكثر الناس جشعا
the other 99 percent of our fellow citizens
نرى 99 في المئة من المواطنين الآخرين
are falling farther and farther behind.
يتخلفون اقتصاديا أكثر فأكثر
In 1980, the top one percent of Americans
في عام 1980، كان نصيب الواحد في المئة الأغنى في امريكا
shared about eight percent of national [income],
8% من الدخل القومي
while the bottom 50 percent of Americans
بينما مجموع دخل ال50% الأفقر
shared 18 percent.
18% من الدخل القومي
Thirty years later, today, the top one percent
واليوم، بعد ثلاثين عاما، يتشارك ال 1% الأكثر ثراء
shares over 20 percent of national [income],
في أكثر من 20% من الدخل القومي
while the bottom 50 percent of Americans
بينما يتشارك ال50% الأكثر فقرا
share 12 or 13.
في 12 أو 13 % من الدخل القومي
If the trend continues,
لو استمر الأمر على هذا المنوال
the top one percent will share
فسيتشارك ال1% الأكثر ثراء
over 30 percent of national [income]
في أكثر من30% من الدخل القومي
in another 30 years,
بعد ثلاثين عاما أخرى
while the bottom 50 percent of Americans
بينما سيتشارك ال50% الأفقر
will share just six.
في 6% فقط من الدخل القومي
You see, the problem isn't that we have
كما ترون، المشكلة ليست في وجود
some inequality.
القليل من اللامساواة
Some inequality is necessary
فهذا أمر ضروري
for a high-functioning capitalist democracy.
في ديمقراطية رأسمالية عالية الأداء
The problem is that inequality
لب المشكلة هو أن اللامساواة
is at historic highs today
قد وصلت لأعلى مستوياتها تاريخيًا
and it's getting worse every day.
والأمر يزداد سوء يوميًا
And if wealth, power, and income
فلو استمرت الثروة والسلطة والدخول العالية
continue to concentrate
في التجمع
at the very tippy top,
في أعلى القمة
our society will change
سيتحول مجتمعنا
from a capitalist democracy
من ديمقراطية رأسمالية
to a neo-feudalist rentier society
إلى مجتمع إقطاعي ريعي جديد
like 18th-century France.
مثل فرنسا في القرن الثامن عشر
That was France
هكذا كانت فرنسا
before the revolution
قبل الثورة
and the mobs with the pitchforks.
كان هناك الغوغائيون بالعصي.
So I have a message for my fellow plutocrats
لذلك لدي رسالة لزملائي البلتوقراطيين.
and zillionaires
وفاحشو الثراء.
and for anyone who lives
ولأجل كل شخص يعيش
in a gated bubble world:
في عالم فقاعي معزول:
Wake up.
استفيقوا.
Wake up. It cannot last.
استفيقوا. هذا لن يدوم.
Because if we do not do something
لأنه إذ لم نقم بشيء
to fix the glaring economic inequities in our society,
لإصلاح اللامساواة الاقتصادية في مجتمعنا،
the pitchforks will come for us,
فسوف تأتي العصىّ من أجلنا،
for no free and open society can long sustain
حيث لن تبقى الحرية والمجتمع المنفتح طويلًا
this kind of rising economic inequality.
هذا النوع من ارتفاع اللامساواة الاقتصادية.
It has never happened. There are no examples.
لم يحدث من قبل. لا توجد أمثلة.
You show me a highly unequal society,
أرني مجتمعا غير متكافئ للغاية،
and I will show you a police state
وسوف أُريك دولة بوليسية
or an uprising.
أو انتفاضة ما.
The pitchforks will come for us
العصىّ ستتأتى لأجلنا
if we do not address this.
إذا لم نواجه هذا.
It's not a matter of if, it's when.
ليست المسألة ماذا لو؟ لكن متى؟
And it will be terrible when they come
وسيكون فظيعًا عندما يأتي
for everyone,
للجميع،
but particularly for people like us plutocrats.
ولكن سيأتي للبلتوقراطيين بالتحديد.
I know I must sound like some liberal do-gooder.
أعلم بأنني أبدو كفاعل خير ليبرالي.
I'm not. I'm not making a moral argument
لست كذلك. ولا أقوم بجدال أخلاقي
that economic inequality is wrong.
عدم المساواة الاقتصادية هو أمر خاطئ.
What I am arguing is that rising economic inequality
ما أناقشه هو ارتفاع اللامساواة الاقتصادية
is stupid and ultimately self-defeating.
إنه غباء وتدمير ذاتي غير محدود.
Rising inequality doesn't just increase our risks
ارتفاع عدم المساواة لا تزيد من أخطارنا فقط
from pitchforks,
من العصي،
but it's also terrible for business too.
وإنما من الفظاعة التي تحتل الأعمال أيضًا
So the model for us rich guys should be Henry Ford.
ولذلك لابد أن نتمثل نموذج هنري فورد
When Ford famously introduced the $5 day,
عندما قدم فورد عرضه المشهور 5$ لليوم
which was twice the prevailing wage at the time,
هو ضعف الأجور في ذلك الوقت،
he didn't just increase the productivity
لم يضاعف إنتاجية مصانعه
of his factories,
فقط،
he converted exploited autoworkers who were poor
حوّل عمّال صناعة السيارات المُستغلين والفقراء
into a thriving middle class who could now afford
إلى طبقة وسطى مزدهرة استطاعت
to buy the products that they made.
شراء منتجعات قاموا بصناعتها
Ford intuited what we now know is true,
علم فورد بالفطرة ما نعلم بأنه صحيح،
that an economy is best understood as an ecosystem
بأن الاقتصاد يفهم بشكل جيد كنظام بيئي
and characterized by the same kinds
ويتسم بنفس أنواع
of feedback loops you find
حلقات ردود الفعل التي تجدها
in a natural ecosystem,
في النظام البيئي الطبيعي،
a feedback loop between customers and businesses.
ردود الفعل المتبادلة بين العملاء والأعمال.
Raising wages increases demand,
وزيادة الأجور زادت من طلبات التقدم
which increases hiring,
مما زاد التوظيف
which in turn increases wages
والذي بدوره يزيد الأجور
and demand and profits,
والطلب والأرباح،
and that virtuous cycle of increasing prosperity
وهذه الدورة من زيادة الرخاء
is precisely what is missing
هي بالتحديد ما هو مفقود
from today's economic recovery.
من المعالجة الاقتصادية اليوم.
And this is why we need to put behind us
ولهذا السبب نحتاج للتخلي عن
the trickle-down policies that so dominate
السياسات التدريجية التي تهيمن بشدة
both political parties
على كلا الأحزاب السياسية
and embrace something I call middle-out economics.
وتبني ما أسميه (الاقتصاديات المتوسطة)
Middle-out economics rejects
يرفض الاقتصاد التدريجي المتوسط
the neoclassical economic idea
الفكرة الاقتصادية الكلاسيكية الجديدة
that economies are efficient, linear, mechanistic,
هذه الاقتصاديات تتسم بالكفاءة والخطية والآلية
that they tend towards equilibrium and fairness,
بحيث تتسم بالتوازن والإنصاف
and instead embraces the 21st-century idea
وبدلا من احتضان فكرة القرن 21
that economies are complex, adaptive,
هذه الاقتصاديات معقدة وتكيفية،
ecosystemic,
ومنظمة بيئيًا
that they tend away from equilibrium and toward inequality,
بحيث تتجه نحو التوازن وعدم المساواة
that they're not efficient at all
هذه ليست فعالة على الأطلاق
but are effective if well managed.
ولكنها ستكون كذلك لو تمت إدارتها كما يجب
This 21st-century perspective
منظور القرن 21 هذا
allows you to clearly see that capitalism
يسمح لك أن ترى هذه الرأسمالية بوضوح
does not work by [efficiently] allocating
لا يعمل بشكل (متكافئ) بتخصيص
existing resources.
الموارد الحالية
It works by [efficiently] creating new solutions
أنه يعمل (بكفاءة) لخلق حلول جديدة
to human problems.
لمشاكل الإنسان
The genius of capitalism
عبقرية الرأسمالية
is that it is an evolutionary solution-finding system.
أنها نظام بحثي للحلول التطورية
It rewards people for solving other people's problems.
أنه يوجه الناس لحل مشكلاتهم.
The difference between a poor society
الفرق بين المجتمع الفقير
and a rich society, obviously,
والمجتمع الغنى، بوضوح،
is the degree to which that society
هي الدرجة التي يخلقها
has generated solutions in the form
المجتمع كحلول في شكل
of products for its citizens.
منتجات لأجل مواطنيه.
The sum of the solutions
إن مجموعة الحلول
that we have in our society
التي لدى مجتمعنا
really is our prosperity, and this explains
هي بالضبط الرخاء الذي نعيشه وهذا يفسر
why companies like Google and Amazon
لماذا شركات مثل جوجل وأمازون
and Microsoft and Apple
وميكروسوفت وآبل
and the entrepreneurs who created those companies
ورواد الأعمال الذين أنشؤوها
have contributed so much
ساهموا كثيرًا
to our nation's prosperity.
في رخاء أمتنا
This 21st-century perspective
منظور القرن 21 هذا
also makes clear
يوضح بشدة
that what we think of as economic growth
أن النمو الاقتصادي الذي نفكر فيه
is best understood as
يُفهم بشكل أفضل
the rate at which we solve problems.
على ضوء مدى حلنا للمشكلات.
But that rate is totally dependent upon
لكن ذلك المعدل يعتمد بالكامل على
how many problem solvers —
عدد المختصين المختلفين في حل المشكلات
diverse, able problem solvers — we have,
التي لدينا
and thus how many of our fellow citizens
وكم عدد زملائنا المواطنين
actively participate,
المشاركين بفعالية
both as entrepreneurs who can offer solutions,
كرواد الأعمال يعرضون الحلول
and as customers who consume them.
وعملاء يستهلكونها في نفس الوقت
But this maximizing participation thing
لكن تعظيم المشاركة هذا يعتبر شيء
doesn't happen by accident.
لا يحدث صدفة
It doesn't happen by itself.
ولا يحدث بنفسه
It requires effort and investment,
بل يتطلب مجهودا واستثمارا
which is why all
ولهذا السبب تعد كل
highly prosperous capitalist democracies
الديمقراطيات الرأسمالية المزدهرة الرفيعة
are characterized by massive investments
متميزة باستثمارات هائلة
in the middle class and the infrastructure
في الطبقة المتوسطة والبنية التحتية
that they depend on.
حيث تعتمد عليها
We plutocrats need to get this
نحن البلوتقراطيون نحتاج لترك هذه
trickle-down economics thing behind us,
الاقتصاديات المنحدرة خلفنا
this idea that the better we do,
هذه الفكرة هي أفضل ما نفعل
the better everyone else will do.
هذ أفضل ما يمكن لأحد أن يفعله.
It's not true. How could it be?
ليس حقيقيا. ماذا سيحدث؟
I earn 1,000 times the median wage,
أن أجنى ضعف متوسطي الأجور 1000 مرة
but I do not buy 1,000 times as much stuff,
ولكنني لا أشترى أشياء بكثرة بمعدل 1000 مرة
do I?
أليس كذلك؟
I actually bought two pairs of these pants,
في الواقع أنا اشترى زوجا من هذه السراويل
what my partner Mike calls
ذلك ما يدعوه رفيقي مايك
my manager pants.
سراويلي الإدارية
I could have bought 2,000 pairs,
فأنا أستطيع شراء 2000 زوج،
but what would I do with them? (Laughter)
ولكن ماذا أفعل بها؟
How many haircuts can I get?
كم عدد قصات الشعر التي بإمكاني الحصول عليها؟
How often can I go out to dinner?
كم بإمكاني الخروج للعشاء؟
No matter how wealthy a few plutocrats get,
مهما حاز بضعة بلوتوقراطين على الثراء
we can never drive a great national economy.
لن يمكن قيادة الاقتصاد الوطني الهائل
Only a thriving middle class can do that.
فقط الطبقة الوسطى المزدهرة يمكنها فعل ذلك.
There's nothing to be done,
ليس هناك شيء لفعله
my plutocrat friends might say.
ربما يقول أصدقائي البلتوقراطيون
Henry Ford was in a different time.
حقبة هنري فورد كانت مختلفة.
Maybe we can't do some things.
ربما لا يمكننا فعل بعض الأشياء
Maybe we can do some things.
وربما يمكننا فعل البعض الآخر
June 19, 2013,
في 19 يونيو 2013
Bloomberg published an article I wrote called
نشرت بلومبرج مقالة كتبتها بعنوان
"The Capitalist’s Case for a $15 Minimum Wage."
"حجاج رأسمالي من أجل 15$ كحد أدنى للأجور"
The good people at Forbes magazine,
الناس الجيدون في مجلة فوربز
among my biggest admirers,
من بين أكبر المعجبين بي،
called it "Nick Hanauer's near-insane proposal."
دعوها " الاقتراح شبه المجنون ل نيك هنور"
And yet, just 350 days
وبعد 350 يوما فقط
after that article was published,
بعد نشر المقال
Seattle's Mayor Ed Murray signed into law
وقع إي دي مورى عمدة سياتل على قانون
an ordinance raising the minimum wage in Seattle
ينص على رفع معدل الحد الأدنى للأجور في سياتل
to 15 dollars an hour,
إلى 15 دولار في الساعة،
more than double
أكثر من الضعف
what the prevailing federal $7.25 rate is.
فالمعدل الفيدرالي السائد هو 7.25$
How did this happen,
كيف حدث هذا،
reasonable people might ask.
ربما يسأل العقلانيون.
It happened because a group of us
أنه حدث بسبب تذكر مجموعة منا
reminded the middle class
الطبقة المتوسطة
that they are the source
التي تعد مصدر النمو
of growth and prosperity in capitalist economies.
والرخاء في الاقتصاديات الرأسمالية
We reminded them that when workers have more money,
فنحن تذكرناهم عندما اكتسب العاملون مالًا أكثر،
businesses have more customers,
الشركات لديها العديد من المستهلكون
and need more employees.
وتحتاج للعديد من الموظفين
We reminded them that when businesses
تذكرناهم عندما دَفعت الشركات
pay workers a living wage,
للعاملين أجرا معيشيا
taxpayers are relieved of the burden
يرتاح دافعو الضرائب من عاتق
of funding the poverty programs
تمويل برامج مكافحة الفقر
like food stamps and medical assistance
كطوابع الطعام والمساعدات الطبية
and rent assistance
والمساعدة فيما يتعلق بالاكتراء
that those workers need.
فهذا ما يحتاجه العاملون
We reminded them that low-wage workers
فنحن نذكرهم بأن العمال ذوي الأجور المتدنية
make terrible taxpayers,
يقومون بدفع ضرائب مروعة
and that when you raise the minimum wage
وهذا عند رفع الحد الأدنى للأجور
for all businesses,
للشركات كلها،
all businesses benefit
فكل الشركات تستفيد
yet all can compete.
وبعد كل هذا تكون قادرة على المنافسة
Now the orthodox reaction, of course,
الآن سيكون رد فعل الأرثوذكس بالطبع،
is raising the minimum wage costs jobs. Right?
هو رفع تكلفة وظائف الحد الأدنى للأجور أليس كذلك؟
Your politician's always echoing
يردد السياسي دائمًا
that trickle-down idea by saying things like,
تلك الفكرة التدريجية بالقول،
"Well, if you raise the price of employment,
"إذا قمت بزيادة سعر العمالة،
guess what happens? You get less of it."
احزر ما سيحدث ستحصل على القليل منه تماما"
Are you sure?
هل أنت متأكد؟
Because there's some contravening evidence.
لأن هناك بعض الأدلة التي تتعارض مع ذلك.
Since 1980, the wages of CEOs in our country
منذ 1980، انتقلت أجور المديرين التنفيذين
have gone from about 30 times the median wage
في بلدنا من 30 ضعف متوسطي الأجور
to 500 times.
الى 500 ضعف
That's raising the price of employment.
هذا يزيد سعر العمالة.
And yet, to my knowledge,
وحتى الآن، على حد علمي
I have never seen a company
لم أر شركة أبدًا
outsource its CEO's job, automate their job,
تعهد بوظائف المديرين التنفيذيين،
export the job to China.
للصين بشكل آلي.
In fact, we appear to be employing
في الواقع، يبدو أننا نوّظف
more CEOs and senior managers than ever before.
العديد من المديرين التنفيذين والمدراء أكثر من أي وقت مضى.
So too for technology workers
وهكذا بالنسبة لعمال التكنولوجيا
and financial services workers,
وعمال الخدمات المالية
who earn multiples of the median wage
الذين يكسبون مضاعفات من متوسط الأجور
and yet we employ more and more of them,
لا زلنا نوظف الكثير والكثير منهم
so clearly you can raise the price of employment
لذلك بوضوح يمكنك زيادة سعر العمالة
and get more of it.
والحصول على المزيد منهم.
I know that most people
أعلم بأن معظم الناس
think that the $15 minimum wage
يفكرون بأن يكون متوسط الأجور15$
is this insane, risky economic experiment.
يعتبر جنونا، تجربة اقتصادية خطيرة.
We disagree.
نحن نختلف.
We believe that the $15 minimum wage
نحن نعتقد بأن 15$ كحد أدنى للأجور
in Seattle
في سياتل
is actually the continuation
هي في الواقع تعد استمرارية
of a logical economic policy.
لسياسة اقتصادية معقولة.
It is allowing our city
إنها تسمح لمدينتنا
to kick your city's ass.
بالتفوق على مدينتك.
Because, you see,
لأنه، أتعلم،
Washington state already has
لدى ولاية واشنطن بالفعل
the highest minimum wage
أعلى متوسط للأجور
of any state in the nation.
بالمقارنة مع أي ولاية في الدولة
We pay all workers $9.32,
فنحن ندفع لكل العمال 9.32$
which is almost 30 percent more
والذي يعتبر أعلى بنسبة 30% تقريبًا
than the federal minimum of 7.25,
من الحد الأدنى الفيدرالي والذي هو 7.25،
but crucially, 427 percent more
لكن، وبشكل حاسم، 427% أكثر من
than the federal tipped minimum of 2.13.
الحد الأدنى الفيدرالي للبقشيش، والذي هو 2.13
If trickle-down thinkers were right,
إذا كان الناصحون بالنظام التدريجي محقين،
then Washington state should have massive unemployment.
إذًا فعلى ولاية واشنطن مواجهة البطالة الرهيبة
Seattle should be sliding into the ocean.
ولنغرق ولاية سياتل في المحيط.
And yet, Seattle
ومع ذلك فإن سياتل
is the fastest-growing big city in the country.
هي أسرع مدينة نموًا في البلاد.
Washington state is generating small business jobs
توفر ولاية واشنطن وظائف في المقاولات الصغرى
at a higher rate than any other major state
بمعدل أعلى مقارنة بأي ولاية كبرى
in the nation.
في البلد كله.
The restaurant business in Seattle? Booming.
شركات المطاعم في سياتل؟ مزدهرة.
Why? Because the fundamental law of capitalism is,
لماذا؟ لأن القانون الأساسي للرأسمالية هو
when workers have more money,
عندما يحصل العاملون على مال أكثر
businesses have more customers
ستكتسب الشركات عملاء جدد
and need more workers.
فتحتاج إلى عاملين أكثر
When restaurants pay restaurant workers enough
عندما تدفع المطاعم للعاملين ما يكفي
so that even they can afford to eat in restaurants,
لدرجة تجعلهم يتحملون الأكل بالمطاعم
that's not bad for the restaurant business.
هذا ليس سيء بالنسبة لأعمال المطاعم.
That's good for it,
هذا جيد بالنسبة لهم
despite what some restaurateurs may tell you.
برغم ما يقوله بعض أصحاب المطاعم لك
Is it more complicated than I'm making out?
أنها أكثر تعقيدًا مما بإمكاني فعله؟
Of course it is.
بالطبع هي كذلك.
There are a lot of dynamics at play.
هناك كثير من العوامل المؤثرة.
But can we please stop insisting
لكن هل لنا أن نتوقف عن الإصرار
that if low-wage workers earn a little bit more,
هذا إذا اكتسب عمال الحد الأدنى من الأجر أكثر قليلًا،
unemployment will skyrocket
ستتصاعد البطالة بشكل صاروخي
and the economy will collapse?
وسينهار الاقتصاد؟
There is no evidence for it.
ليس هناك دليل على ذلك.
The most insidious thing
الأمر الأكثر مكرًا
about trickle-down economics
عن الاقتصاديات التدريجية
is not the claim that if the rich get richer,
ليس أن الغنىّ سوف يصير أكثر غنى،
everyone is better off.
وأن الجميع سوف يصير أفضل حالًا.
It is the claim made by those who oppose
إنه الإدعاء الذي يروج له المعترضون
any increase in the minimum wage
على أي زيادة للحد الأدنى للأجور
that if the poor get richer,
إذا أصبح الفقراء أكثر غنى،
that will be bad for the economy.
هذا سوف يصبح سيئًا للاقتصاد.
This is nonsense.
هذا هراء.
So can we please dispense with this rhetoric
لهذا هل يمكننا الاستغناء عن هذه النبرة
that says that rich guys like me
التي تقول بأن الأغنياء مثلي
and my plutocrat friends
وأصدقائي البلوتقراطيون
made our country?
هم سبب نهضة هذه الأمة؟
We plutocrats know,
نحن البلوتقراطيون نعلم،
even if we don't like to admit it in public,
حتى وإن لم نفضل أن نعلن ذلك علنًا
that if we had been born somewhere else,
وهذا في حالة ولادتنا في مكان آخر،
not here in the United States,
ليس هنا في الولايات المتحدة
we might very well be just some dude standing barefoot
فنحن ربما كنا لنكون حافيي القدمين
by the side of a dirt road selling fruit.
نبيع الفاكهة بجانب طريق قذر.
It's not that they don't have good entrepreneurs in other places,
هذا ليس بسبب افتقادهم لرواد الأعمال في أماكنهم
even very, very poor places.
أو حتى في الأماكن الفقيرة جدًا
It's just that that's all
إنه فقط بسبب
that those entrepreneurs' customers can afford.
أن عملاء رواد الأعمال يستطيعون التحمل.
So here's an idea for a new kind of economics,
لهذا هناك فكرة لهذا النوع من الاقتصاديات
a new kind of politics
“مفهوم جديد من السياسة"
that I call new capitalism.
والتي أدعوها "رأسمالية جديدة"
Let's acknowledge that capitalism
فدعونا نعترف بأن الرأسمالية
beats the alternatives,
تقضي على البدائل
but also that the more people we include,
لكن بقدر ما نقوم بضم أشخاص أكثر
both as entrepreneurs and as customers,
سواء كرواد أعمال أو عملاء
the better it works.
تشتغل بشكل أفضل.
Let's by all means shrink the size of government,
لذلك دعونا نقلص من حجم الحكومة بكل المعاني
but not by slashing the poverty programs,
ليس ذلك من خلال خفض برامج الفقر
but by ensuring that workers are paid enough
لكن بالتأكيد على أن العاملين يُدفع لهم ما يكفي
so that they actually don't need those programs.
لذلك في الواقع هم لا يحتاجون لهذه البرامج
Let's invest enough in the middle class
دعونا نستثمر ما يكفي في الطبقة المتوسطة
to make our economy fairer and more inclusive,
لجعل اقتصادنا أكثر عدلًا وشمولية
and by fairer, more truly competitive,
وعندما يكون "أكثر عدلًا"، ستكون هناك منافسة حقيقية
and by more truly competitive,
ومن خلال منافسة حقيقية أكبر
more able to generate the solutions
ستكون هناك قدرة أكثر على توليد الحلول
to human problems
للمشاكل الإنسانية
that are the true drivers of growth and prosperity.
هؤلاء هم قادة التنمية والرخاء
Capitalism is the greatest social technology
الرأسمالية هي أعظم تكنولوجيا اجتماعية
ever invented
تم اختراعها حتى الآن
for creating prosperity in human societies,
لخلق الرخاء في المجتمعات الإنسانية
if it is well managed,
إذا تم تنظيمها جيدًا،
but capitalism, because of the fundamental
لكن الرأسمالية، بسبب الديناميكيات المضاعفة
multiplicative dynamics of complex systems,
الأساسية للأنظمة المعقدة
tends towards, inexorably, inequality,
تميل نحو، عدم الرحمة وعدم المساواة
concentration and collapse.
والتركيز والانهيار.
The work of democracies
عمل الديمقراطيات
is to maximize the inclusion of the many
هو من أجل تعظيم شمل العديد
in order to create prosperity,
لخلق الرخاء
not to enable the few to accumulate money.
لا لتمكين قلة من جمع المال.
Government does create prosperity and growth,
الحكومة لا تخلق الازدهار والتنمية،
by creating the conditions that allow
بخلق الظروف التي تسمح
both entrepreneurs and their customers
لكل من رواد العمال وعملائهم
to thrive.
بالازدهار.
Balancing the power of capitalists like me
موازنة قوة الرأسماليين مثلي
and workers isn't bad for capitalism.
والعاملين ليست بالأمر السيئ بالنسبة للرأسمالية.
It's essential to it.
بل هي ضرورية لها.
Programs like a reasonable minimum wage,
البرامج مثل الحد الأدنى المعقول للأجور،
affordable healthcare,
والرعاية الصحية المعقولة،
paid sick leave,
الإجازة المرضية المدفوعة،
and the progressive taxation necessary
والضرائب التصاعدية الضرورية
to pay for the important infrastructure
لدفع البنية التحتية الهامة
necessary for the middle class like education, R and D,
الضرورية للطبقة المتوسطة كالتعليم، والبحث والتطوير
these are indispensable tools
هذه أدوات لا غنى عنها
shrewd capitalists should embrace
الرأسماليون الدهاة عليهم أن يتبنو
to drive growth, because no one benefits from it
توجيه النمو، حيث لا يستفيد أحد منه
like us.
مثلنا.
Many economists would have you believe
العديد من الاقتصاديات
that their field is an objective science.
ستجعلك تعتقد أن مجالهم هو علم موضوعي.
I disagree, and I think that it is equally
أنا أختلف، وأعتقد أن هذا يساوي
a tool that humans use
الأداة التي يستخدمها البشر
to enforce and encode
لفرض وترميز
our social and moral preferences and prejudices
أفضليتنا الأخلاقية والاجتماعية والأحكام المسبقة
about status and power,
حول المكانة والقوة،
which is why plutocrats like me
ولهذا السبب يسعى البلوتقراطيون مثلي
have always needed to find persuasive stories
دائما لإيجاد قصص مقنعة
to tell everyone else
لإخبار الآخرين بها
about why our relative positions
لتفسير كيف أن أوضاعنا النسبية
are morally righteous and good for everyone:
صالحة أخلاقيًا وجيدة للجميع:
like, we are indispensable, the job creators,
من قبيل أنه لا يمكن الاستغناء عنا، وأننا نخلق الوظائف،
and you are not;
أما أنتم فلا.
like, tax cuts for us create growth,
مثل، خفض الضريبة لدينا يخلق نموا،
but investments in you
والاستثمارات فيكم
will balloon our debt
ستضخم ديوننا
and bankrupt our great country;
وتفلس بلدنا العظيم.
that we matter;
لذلك نحن مهمون.
that you don't.
أما أنت فلا.
For thousands of years, these stories were called
لآلاف السنين، هذه القصص كانت تدعي
divine right.
الحق الإلهي.
Today, we have trickle-down economics.
اليوم، لدينا اقتصاديات تدريجية.
How obviously, transparently self-serving
فأصبحت الخدمة الذاتية واضحة وشفافة
all of this is.
بشكل بديهي.
We plutocrats need to see
نحن البلتقراطيون نحتاج لأن نرى
that the United States of America made us,
أن الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية خلقتنا،
not the other way around;
وليس العكس:
that a thriving middle class is the source
أن طبقة وسطى مزدهرة هي مصدر
of prosperity in capitalist economies,
الازدهار في اقتصاديات الرأسمالية،
not a consequence of it.
وليس نتيجة لذلك.
And we should never forget
ولا يجب أن ننسى أبدًا
that even the best of us in the worst of circumstances
بأن حتى الأفضل بيننا في أحلك الظروف
are barefoot by the side of a dirt road selling fruit.
سيكون حافي القدمين على جانب طريق قذر يبيع الفاكهة.
Fellow plutocrats, I think it may be time for us
زملائي البلتقراطيون، أعتقد بأنه حان الوقت لنا
to recommit to our country,
لإعادة إلزام بلدنا،
to commit to a new kind of capitalism
بنوع جديد من الرأسمالية
which is both more inclusive and more effective,
تكون أكثر شمولية وفعالية في ذات الوقت،
a capitalism that will ensure
رأسمالية تضمن
that America's economy remains
أن يظل الاقتصاد الأمريكي
the most dynamic and prosperous in the world.
الأكثر ديناميكية وازدهارا في العالم
Let's secure the future for ourselves,
دعونا نؤمن المستقبل لأنفسنا،
our children and their children.
لأطفالنا وأطفالهم.
Or alternatively, we could do nothing,
أو بدل ذلك، ألا نفعل شيئًا،
hide in our gated communities
نختبئ في مجتمعاتنا المبوّبة
and private schools,
والمدارس الخاصة،
enjoy our planes and yachts
مستمتعين بطائراتنا ويخوتنا
— they're fun —
- إنها ممتعة -
and wait for the pitchforks.
منتظرين العصي.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)